<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wajda's 'Korczak' Sets Loose the Furies</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="437155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAZI ERA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WARSAW (POLAND)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAJDA, ANDRZEJ</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">KORCZAK (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland/Warsaw</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D91238F937A25757C0A967958260" item-length="1759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wajda's 'Korczak' Sets Loose the Furies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WARSAW</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the closing shot of Andrzej Wajda's new film, "Korczak," a cattle car crammed with Jewish children from the Warsaw ghetto rumbles toward the Treblinka concentration camp. Suddenly the action shifts to slow motion, and the car uncouples from the train as if touched by an unseen hand. Its doors slide open, and the children spill happy and laughing into a verdant field.</p>
        <p>The film, which opened Friday in New York, recounts the life and death of Janusz Korczak (pronounced YAN-oosh KOR-chak), a Jewish teacher, doctor and writer who struggled in vain to save 200 children living in his orphanage in the Warsaw ghetto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the closing shot of Andrzej Wajda's new film, "Korczak," a cattle car crammed with Jewish children from the Warsaw ghetto rumbles toward the Treblinka concentration camp. Suddenly the action shifts to slow motion, and the car uncouples from the train as if touched by an unseen hand. Its doors slide open, and the children spill happy and laughing into a verdant field.</p>
        <p>The film, which opened Friday in New York, recounts the life and death of Janusz Korczak (pronounced YAN-oosh KOR-chak), a Jewish teacher, doctor and writer who struggled in vain to save 200 children living in his orphanage in the Warsaw ghetto.</p>
        <p>Its concluding 30 seconds of fantasy have become the focal point of a bitter assault on the movie by French critics, some of whom viewed it as an attempt by Poles to throw a rosy wash over their own complicity, or indifference, to the genocide of Jews. By contrast, Israeli critics praised the ending as a symbol of hope, and Mr. Wajda (pronounced VIE-da) said the country's Ministry of Education had added the film to the required school curriculum.</p>
        <p>Numbered among its vigorous detractors are Claude Lanzmann, director of "Shoah," the epic 1985 documentary on the Holocaust; its defenders include Marek Edelman, the Polish Jew who is the only surviving leader of the 1944 Warsaw ghetto uprising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wajda, who earned his reputation as the best known of Poland's film makers with a series of movies that challenged the Communist regime, is a grandfatherly man with a shock of white hair. The 65-year-old Mr. Wajda said he had no intention of obscuring the historical fact, noted in the film's postscript, that Dr. Korczak and the children died in the gas chambers of Treblinka in 1942.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wajda argued that movie makers have a duty to leave their audience with something more. He said he never considered ending the film with its penultimate shot, which shows the train speeding away from Warsaw toward the concentration camp.</p>
        <p>"Such an ending would have said to me that all these endeavors of Dr. Korczak were sunk in a black hole; that pedagogy in the face of force has no sense; that no efforts of man can reverse the fact that he is dying so accidentally. This would be an awful, existentialist point of view.</p>
        <p>"There would have been nothing easier than showing the death of the children in the gas chamber," Mr. Wajda. "It would have been a very moving scene. Everyone would have been crying. But do we have the right, does art have the right to show this? Is art for this?</p>
        <p>"Isn't art for telling it in some different way? Art has to stop short of certain facts, has to look for other possibilities. It seems to me that it is beautiful that when we do not agree to the fact that the children were gassed, we create a legend that these children go somewhere, into some better world."</p>
        <p>Mr. Wajda, who has previously benefited from largely sympathetic coverage by the world press, seems startled to be so much on the defensive. The movie was not a commercial success in Poland.</p>
        <p>One of the most prominent intellectuals to support the Solidarity movement, he is widely regarded as the leading director working today in Polish cinema. For decades, he stretched the Communist-run film system to its limits, defying explicit censorship and implicit constraints of Government financing to produce movies that defined the nation's political consciousness.</p>
        <p>In 1956, shortly after the end of Stalinism, he released a movie that depicted a resistance group trying to escape from the Nazi attack through the sewers of Warsaw. All eventually died in the maze. The movie, "Kanal," won the Special Jury Prize at the Cannes International Film Festival in 1957, and it seemed to sum up how many Poles felt about escaping Nazism only to be forced to accept Soviet Communism. Later he made such films as "Ashes and Diamonds" (1958), "Hunting Flies" (1969) and "Man of Marble" (1977).</p>
        <p>Mr. Wajda's 1981 film "Men of Iron" captured the heady exhilaration that accompanied the early days of the Solidarity movement. It portrayed the rise of an anti-Communist leader, a former student, who takes a job in the Gdansk shipyard after his father is killed in the workers' rebellion of 1970.</p>
        <p>Even as he made other movies in the past 15 years, Mr. Wajda said, he had been quietly hoping to bring the story of Dr. Korczak to the screen. It was a rare chance, he said, to illuminate the dark corners of the Polish-Jewish relationship.</p>
        <p>Born in 1878 in Warsaw as Henryk Goldszmit, the doctor adopted the name Korczak for literary purposes. He was raised in a secular household and grew up believing that Jews could find a place as participants within the Polish nation. As a noted scholar and lecturer on pediatrics, he found his sense of Jewish identity intensifying when he confronted the virulent anti-Semitism that characterized Polish social and political life in the late 1930's.</p>
        <p>Before World War II, three million Jews, about 10 percent of the population, lived in Poland. All but a few hundred thousand perished in concentration camps, and nearly all of the remainder emigrated after the Polish Government's 1968 anti-Jewish campaign.</p>
        <p>Throughout the Communist years, the intertwined history of Poles and Jews was a taboo subject for writers and film makers. The painful process of coming to terms with history that confronted West Germans and, to some extent, the French, was thus postponed in Poland. Mr. Wajda said he had long been eager to begin filling that void.</p>
        <p>When the political warming of the mid-1970's touched Poland, Mr. Wajda said, he began collaborating with an American producer. As originally conceived by the American, Mr. Wajda said, the movie was to be a Polish version of "Dr. Zhivago," recounting Dr. Korczak's journey from service in the 1905 Russo-Japanese war to death in Treblinka. There were hopes that Richard Dreyfuss would play the lead, a role that eventually went to the eminent Polish actor Wojtek Pszoniak. The Warsaw ghetto was to form only a small part of the movie.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wajda balked at this idea for several reasons. He saw in Dr. Korczak's years in the ghetto a story that had to be filmed by a Polish director and aimed first at the Polish audience. He was reluctant to work with an American actor, even a famous one who brought with him the possibility of box-office success.</p>
        <p>"What is a director like me afraid of?" Mr. Wajda asked. "He is afraid to make a film without nationality.  Films created in which the director is one nationality, the script is written by someone else and the actors come from different lands and different languages, this combination almost never works."</p>
        <p>Filming, with a group of European backers, began in late 1989, shortly after Mr. Wajda was elected to a seat in the Polish legislature on the Solidarity slate. The director chose to work in black and white, which gives the film a stark texture and allowed him to intersperse his scenes with archival footage of the Warsaw ghetto shot by German photographers.</p>
        <p>The movie had its premiere last year at Cannes, and its reception rocked Mr. Wajda.</p>
        <p>It opened just a few days after France had suffered national shame, and remorse, over the desecration of Jewish graves in the town of Carpentras. An emotional review by Daniele Heymann in Le Monde attacked Mr. Wajda for showing Poles in what she contended was an overly favorable light.</p>
        <p>"Whom do we see around Korczak, played with understandable pleasure by Wojtek Pszoniak?" she wrote. "Germans (obviously brutal) and Jews, resigned or collaborating. There are no Poles. The Warsaw ghetto? This is a matter between Jews and Germans. This is what the Pole wants to convince us of."</p>
        <p>"The suffering with which one views this film grows as it is being screened until the final scene, when the heart leaps to the throat. The deportation order has been signed. The liquidation of the ghetto begins. With a flag bearing the Star of David over their heads, the children, together with Dr. Korczak, enter the cattle car singing.</p>
        <p>"At that moment, the door of the car opens and an ironic, exceptionally disgusting ending takes place: little victims, freshened up and laughing, leave their death car in slow motion. Treblinka as redemption of Jewish children? No. Many times no. Neither in the hour of the Carpentras provocation, or ever."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lanzmann, the director of "Shoah," told newspaper interviewers that he believed Mr. Wajda had deliberately omitted mention of the Poles' passivity and, in some cases, active assistance, to German occupiers carrying out Hitler's "final solution."</p>
        <p>After the reviews appeared, a distributor was found who was willing to market the film in France. Meanwhile, several prominent Polish Jews came to Mr. Wajda's defense. Dr. Edelman, a cardiologist and Warsaw ghetto survivor, wrote a letter to Le Monde praising Mr. Wajda for his support of Solidarity and accusing French critics of "a new, anti-Polish chauvinism which is also a victory of Hitlerism."</p>
        <p>The controversy in France, which was closely covered in the Polish press as it continued this year, touches one of the Poles' rawest nerves. Recently, the Roman Catholic Church acknowledged that some Poles did not do enough to protect Jews during World War II. And some leading intellectuals here have been troubled by the revival of anti-Semitism in the 1990 presidential campaign and by the comments of Lech Walesa that Jews in politics should "identify" themselves publicly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walesa has since emphatically retracted his remarks and denounced anti-Semitism. The issue nonetheless persists in Poland. Just this week, for example, Mr. Wajda was one of several prominent Poles who signed a letter that appeared in a Warsaw newspaper decrying the continued desecration of Jewish monuments in Warsaw.</p>
        <p>Still, Poles bridle at being depicted as a nation of anti-Semites and were particularly incensed at the attacks coming from France, a country with its own problematic record in World War II.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wajda said he was most hurt by those who questioned his intentions. "This was a topic that we should have worked on since 1945," he said. "We should have been doing everything possible to heal this wound, but the Communists were doing everything possible to manipulate it, and this wound was not healed at all.</p>
        <p>"Those who attempted to do something, better or worse, with great or small artistic and intellectual luck, are those who mean well for this issue. I didn't expect that the film could not be criticized. But you cannot question my good intentions."</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
